<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
    <dc:identifier>context:depcha.deutscherorden</dc:identifier>
    <dc:title>Amtsbücher des Deutschen Ordens um 1450. Pflegeamt zu Seehesten und Vogtei zu Leipe, OF 186</dc:title>
    <dc:subject>Business Accounts</dc:subject>
    <dc:description>The economic activities of the Teutonic Order in Prussia in the late Middle Ages are documented in extensive official records, such as debt books, handbooks, and invoices, which provide insights into the economic history of the Order. The official books of the bailiwick of Leipe and the caretaker's office of Seehesten, which have been made accessible in this edition, provide information about the activities of the lower officials of the Teutonic Order around 1450. Bailiffs and caretakers administered income in kind such as grain or chickens and recorded corresponding information in official books. Furthermore, the scribes also noted descriptions of territories or information about rights of use of fields, lakes and rivers. Thus, the official books recorded as Order folios 186 and 186a provide a good basis for answering questions about economic, social, legal and administrative history.</dc:description>
    <dc:publisher>Institute Centre for Information Modelling, University of Graz</dc:publisher>
    <dc:contributor>Elisabeth Raunig</dc:contributor>
   
    <dc:date>1450</dc:date>
    <dc:coverage>Lübbenau/Spreewald, Germany</dc:coverage>
    <dc:coverage>Seehesten, Poland</dc:coverage>
    <dc:language>de</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
    <dc:relation>https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/17IHwXtivgvGWWwnA8BO2nNZbyGcKDpW4gQK7rAnNx4U/edit#slide=id.gb575f404de_2_117</dc:relation>
    <dc:format>XML/TEI</dc:format>
    <dc:type>Collection</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
