<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en">DEPCHA - Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative for Historical
                    Accounts</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:lang="de">Karl-Franzens-Universität Graz</publisher>
                <publisher xml:lang="en">University of Graz</publisher>
                <date when="2018">2018</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date when="2018">2018</date>
                <name type="place">Graz, Austria</name>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
                <div type="header">
                    <head>DEPCHA - The Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative for Historical Accounts</head>
                </div>
                <div>
                     <div type="body"><p>DEPCHA offers publication and access services to a wide range of editors and users
                         interested in the information contained in historical accounting records.
                         This hub allows editors to upload their transcriptions from multiple
                         formats, including Excel, Drupal, XML/TEI. As outputs, the hub offers visualizations.
                         In addition, the hosted dis offerd as Resource Definition Framework (RDF), which
                         makes it discoverable for data mining for historians who seek to take
                         advantage of the semantic web and for researchers in such diverse fields as
                         demography, climate science, and biology. </p>
                     <p>This publishing cooperative would leverage relationships developed under
                         Modeling semantically Enhanced Digital Edition of Accounts (MEDEA), a
                         primarily European-based project funded through a 2015 Bilateral Digital
                         Humanities award from the National Endowment for the Humanities and the
                         German Research Foundation. The cooperative would share technical expertise
                         and establish a platform for publication of digital editions that include
                         textual and numerical representations; visualizations of accounting
                         information; and data representation referencing a shared MEDEA bookkeeping
                         ontology. The proposed platform would replicate a system developed at the
                         Centre for Information Modeling at the University of Graz: the
                         Humanities Asset Management System (Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset
                         Management System - GAMS), a FEDORA Commons based infrastructure for data
                         enrichment, publication, and long-term preservation of digital humanities
                         data.</p></div>
                </div>
            <div>
                <div type="body">
                    <head>Persons involved in the Project</head>
                    <p>A team of experts shares a scholarly affinity for creating digital editions
                         of accounts, with historian Kathryn Tomasek of Wheaton College serving as
                         Principal Investigator. Georg Vogeler and Christopher Pollin join the team
                         from Graz. MEDEA participants lead several U.S. projects focused on creating
                         digital editions of accounts: Jennifer Stertzer and Worthy Martin at the
                         University of Virginia, Anna Agbe-Davies at the University of North Carolina
                         at Chapel Hill, and Jodi Eastberg at Alverno College. Additional
                         participants work in libraries that hold a substantial number of account
                         books in their collections: Molly Hardy of the American Antiquarian Society
                         and Gregory Colati of the University of Connecticut. Ben Brumfield and Sara
                         Brumfield, of Brumfield Labs, LLC, would serve as technical consultants in
                         the United States. Kate Boylan, Director of Archives and Digital
                         Initiatives, would contribute a leadership perspective from Library Services
                         at Wheaton College, the proposed host institution.
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <div type="body">
                <head>GAMS: Long-Term Infrastructure</head>
                <p>The Humanities Asset Management System GAMS (Geisteswissenschaftliches Asset Management System) 
                    provides longterm preservation of research data at the Faculty of Arts and Humanities
                    at the University of Graz. According to the basic understanding of its
                    operator, the Centre for Information Modelling at the University of Graz,
                    the repository not only provides a technical solution, but a way of
                    achieving sustainability in the handling of research data. The aim of GAMS
                    is not only to provide long-term archiving and storage for digital content
                    but to function as a platform for realizing standardized workflows in
                    research projects in the Humanities. In cooperation with scholars from
                    various domains the Centre has been working on questions of the digital
                    representation of textual corpora, source material and other scientific
                    content. Due to the increasing degree of digitization in research, modelling
                    scholarly content has become more and more of an issue in the Humanities and
                    related disciplines.</p>
                <p> The vision of GAMS is to ensure sustainable availability and
                    flexible (re-) use of digitally annotated and enriched scientific content.
                    This is achieved through a largely XML-based content strategy based on
                    domain specific data models. XML-based data formats such as TEI or LIDO
                    provide means for flexible, metadata-enriched forms of storage of textual
                    data. The primary content of documents is enriched with additional
                    descriptive elements based on modelling standards. These standardizations
                    provide a basis for the semantization and, consequently, the automated
                    processing and analysis of specialist knowledge. Special emphasis lies on
                    incorporating domainspecific ontologies and vocabularies. The separation of
                    content and its presentation as a fundamental feature of XML-based formats
                    implies a high degree of flexibility when dealing with the analysis and
                    transformation of the original (textual) data in different presentation
                    forms. On the other hand, this also calls for standardized workflows in the
                    processing of such data. This approach has created a pool of re-usable data
                    objects from the Humanities over the past years. In addition, automatic
                    extraction of semantic relations of the ingested material implement further
                    possibilities of textual analysis and content representation for the
                    designated community of the repository. </p>
                <p> One of the unique features of GAMS is that digital resources are not managed
                    at the file level, but as complex digital objects: the digital
                    representation of a digitized medieval accounting record consists of descriptive
                    metadata, a plurality of facsimile photographs, a TEI-based full-text
                    transcription of the text and so on. All these data streams are stored
                    within an object; every data stream can be seen as an attribute of the
                    object. The design of content models (object classes) construct complex objects and object class
                    hierarchies. Content models not only describe the content structure of an
                    object class (the datastreams) and possible relations to other objects (e.g.
                    container objects) but also bind via WSDL disseminators (methods) to a
                    model. These can be XSL-transformations creating various output formats of
                    the datastreams (HTML, PDF, etc.), the presentation of book-like content in
                    special viewers, or e.g. methods to transform images to other sizes, formats
                    or color models.</p>
                <p> Implementing the aforementioned software design features and respecting the
                    principles of long-term preservation, the GAMS project only uses open source
                    software. Its core technologies are Fedora Commons (currently version 3)
                    for storage and management of digital objects, Apache Lucene and Solr for
                    full text search, Blazegraph Triplestore as graph database, Postgresql
                    Database Server as relational database, Apache Cocoon as main platform for
                    web services used as object disseminators, and Loris IIIF Image Server to
                    provide access to images via the IIIF Image API11. 2017 marked the beginning
                    of a major migration process to ensure accessibility of content for the next
                    years. Therfore a new version of GAMS will be based on Fedora 4.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="body">
                    <head>Data Ingest: Cirilo</head>
                    <p>
                        Cirilo is a java application developed for content preservation and data curation in FEDORA-based repository systems. 
                        Content preservation and data curation in our sense include object creation and management, versioning, normalization and standards, 
                        and the choice of data formats. The client offers functionalities which are especially prone to be used as tools for mass operations on 
                        FEDORA objects, thus complementing FEDORA's inbuilt Admin Client. Cirilo operates on FEDORA's management-API (API-M) and uses a collection of predefined
                        content models. These content models can be used without further adjustments for standard workflow scenarios like the management of collections
                        of TEI objects. Content models in the sense of FEDORA are class definitions; On the one hand they define the (MIME-)type of the contained datastreams,
                        on the other hand they designate dissemination methods operating on these datastreams. Every object in the repository is an instance of one of these class definitions.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Workflow and Data Life Cylye in GAMS</head>
                    <p>
                        The following figure illustrates the data life cycle in the GAMS repository.
                    </p>
                    <figure type="web" source="/context:gams/WORKFLOW" ana="GAMS workflow and data life cycle"/>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <div type="body">
                    <head>Bookkeeping Ontology and Linked Open Data</head>
                    <p>
                         The work of historians is an interpretation of relics from the past. Therefore, when using formal methods on historical data, research should distinguish between the representation of the original source and its interpretation.
                         The latter is the core knowledge domain of historical research. It is advised to share the basic assumptions and definitions in a knowledge domain in a formal way. Linked Open Data is a central approach to this. 
                         This particularly applies to historical accounts, which provide large, highly structured data sets over long timespans, if the individual information entities are prepared for formal analysis.
                    </p>
                     <p>
                         The common knowledge domain of these documents is formalized in a ”bookkeeping” ontology, based on the REA model and compliant with the CIDOC CRM. As a conceptual data model, 
                         the ontology is developed in an iterative process. It formalizes the interpretation of transactions of money, commodities and services from one actor to another, and further
                         properties that can be found in historical accounts. The RDF data extracted from the accounts becomes therefore a highly structured and self describing data set, being interoperable
                         and reusable for researchers in diverse fields. The RDF representation can link to URI’s of commodities, places, persons or other LOD vocabularies.
                         Additionally the RDF representation contributes to the LOD. Thus, all formal methods applied in the DEPCHA project can be transferred to other data conforming to the proposed ontology and any kind of combined data set.
                     </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
            <div type="body">
                <head>Data Modelling</head>
                <p>TO</p>
            </div>
            <div type="body">
                <head>RDF Datamodel</head>
                <p>TO</p>
            </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
