<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title xml:lang="en">DEPCHA - Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative for Historical
					Accounts</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher xml:lang="de">Karl-Franzens-Universität Graz</publisher>
				<publisher xml:lang="en">University of Graz</publisher>
				<date when="2018">2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl/>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p/>
			</projectDesc>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation> <date when="2018">2018</date> <name type="place">Graz, Austria</name> </creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="header">
				<head>DEPCHA - Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative for Historical Accounts</head>
			</div>
			<div>
				<div type="body">
					<p>The Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative for Historical Accounts (DEPCHA)
						project aims to use Semantic Web technologies to display diverse financial
						data from historical documents on a web-based platform. The project's
						objective extends beyond data sharing and long-term preservation to
						developing a web interface featuring exploration, visualization, and
						self-organization capabilities. DEPCHA functions as a discovery and
						publication hub for datasets and digital editions of historical financial
						documents, adhering to the FAIR data principles. The initiative relies on
						GAMS, a Humanities Asset Management System that offers research data
						infrastructure, maintained by the University of Graz's Centre for
						Information Modelling. DEPCHA integrates digital edition functionalities
						with Semantic Web and Linked Open Data concepts to construct a knowledge
						graph detailing the source's various contexts and research emphasis (Vogeler
						2019). An interactive user interface is designed based on this graph for
						exploring and analyzing entities and data from historical sources. A faceted
						analytical display, also known as a dashboard, employs information
						visualization to showcase different perspectives and use cases.</p>
					<div>
						<head>Workflows</head>
						<p> Project collaborators employ various systems, some focusing on data and
							using personal database systems, spreadsheets, or similar environments.
							In these instances, DEPCHA offers a method to convert data to RDF format
							using a CSV template and a Python script that leverages RDFlib (Carl
							2018). Python's adaptability benefits the transformation process, as
							historical information structures and representations differ across
							projects based on research needs. Metadata for the dataset can also be
							incorporated using a simple JSON template. This process is collectively
							called the "dataset" workflow. </p>
						<p> For other partners like editors, the objective is to create a digital
							edition requiring XML/TEI format information. This format is especially
							valuable for historians seeking context-specific information, as digital
							editions allow for additional layers of information beyond digital
							facsimiles, transcriptions, or critically edited texts. The Bookkeeping
							Ontology's semantic layer is expressed through supplementary
							annotations, referred to as the "edition" workflow. A comprehensive
							tutorial for various annotation scenarios in XML/TEI is available at
							<ref target="https://gams.uni-graz.at/o:depcha.tutorial#xml_tei"
							>https://gams.uni-graz.at/o:depcha.tutorial#xml_tei</ref>.</p>
					</div>
					<div>
						<head>Partners</head>
						<p>A group of specialists, united by their academic interest in creating
							digital editions of financial documents</p>
						<list>
							<item>Kathryn Tomasek, Wheaton College</item>
							<item>Jennifer Stertzer, Center for Digital Editing</item>
							<item>Erica Cavanaugh, Center for Digital Editing</item>
							<item>Ben Brumfield, Brumfield Labs</item>
							<item>Sara Brumfield, Brumfield Labs</item>
							<item>Anna Agbe-Davies, University of North Carolina at Chapel
								Hill</item>
							<item>Jodi Eastberg, Alverno College</item>
							<item>Naoki Kokaze, Chiba University</item>
							<item>Hadewijch Masure, Stadsarchief Leuven</item>
							<item>Michal Schmidt, Warsaw</item>
							<item>Michał Slomski, Warsaw</item>
							<item>Anton Büchel</item>
							<item>Laura Morreale</item>
							<item>Nathan Daniels</item>
							<item>Gabriel Viehhauser, Universität Stuttgart</item>
						</list>
					</div>
					<div>
						<head>Publications and Talks</head>
						<list>
							<item> <ref
								target="https://chpollin.github.io/paper/Pollin_MA_2020_Geschichte.pdf"
								>Pollin C.: Digitale, formale Methoden und Modelle in den
								Geschichtswissenschaften. Am Beispiel digital editierter
								historischer Rechnungsbücher, Master Thesis. Graz. 2020.</ref> </item>
							<item> <ref target="https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-2532/paper1.pdf">Pollin C.:
								Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative for Historical Accounts and
								the Bookkeeping Ontology. In: Proceedings of the Doctoral Symposium
								on Research on OnlineDatabases in History (RODBH 2019) Leipzig.
								2019.</ref> </item>
						</list>
						<list>
							<item> <ref
								target="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1CKX9n_kje3jX4q35ryAweL4KeYG2LUCXN2UrMThtM4U/edit#slide=id.gcbe598737f_0_0"
								>Pollin C.: Mapping Semantic Constructs in Historical Domains to
								Visual Structures as Basis for Resource Discovery Using the Example
								of Historical Financial Records. Data for History Conference 2021,
								Berlin. Recording. 30.07.2021. </ref>. <ref
								target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mL43KOMBCJc"
								>Recording</ref>. </item>
							<item> <ref
								target="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1tOW9FhI6elOQDSYCfZanI5Zqc8A5mXL0F8CfsgEtzyw/edit"
								>Pollin C.: “Dashboardfizierung” Historischer Rechnungsbücher.
								Ontologiebasierte Informationsvisualisierung für historische Daten.
								DH-Kolloquium BBAW. 07.05.2021.</ref> </item>
							<item> <ref
								target="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1X5Ul4Uh-KgoH58JSg2MStBMapBZQ7toAccGPrXVszfA/edit"
								>Pollin C.: Modellierung historischer Rechnungsbücher: DEPCHA.
								DH-Kolloquium Uni Köln. Screencast. 22.04.2021.</ref>. <ref
								target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Dsyyhn4iAaY"
								>Screencast</ref> </item>
							<item> <ref
								target="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1-EOOyaMZog6YdYZJ4JMXVqWuTyOEz7uXx-a8Q619-TY/edit#slide=id.g5d67d6e33e_1_0"
								>Pollin C. / Tomasek K.: Making Linkable Data from Account Books:
								Bookkeeping Ontology in the Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative
								for Historical Accounts, TEI Conference 2019, Graz.
								18.11.2019.</ref> </item>
							<item> <ref
								target="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1sO90-1EdHZSGbjGM1MCGeplwbKFlEAL67y5jsYsfw-Y/edit#slide=id.g52707839b8_0_0"
								>Pollin C.: Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative for Historical
								Accounts and the Bookkeeping Ontology. Doctoral Symposium on
								Research on Online Databases in History Leipzig. 04.04.2019.</ref>
							</item>
						</list>
					</div>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back/>
	</text>
</TEI>
