<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en">DEPCHA - Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative for Historical
                    Accounts</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:lang="de">Karl-Franzens-Universität Graz</publisher>
                <publisher xml:lang="en">University of Graz</publisher>
                <date when="2018">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date when="2018">2018</date>
                <name type="place">Graz, Austria</name>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="project">
                <p>Historical financial records provide rich and highly structured administrative
                    sources, containing substantial amounts of individual information. This
                    individual information is often not in the core of research interest. Instead,
                    the records acquire their significance in aggregation of the single entries.
                    Pure transcription does not cover the full range of dimensions of such a source:
                    the linguistic/textual, the quantifiable and the semantic dimension. For
                    research purpose, historical sources are subject to a transformation process
                    towards (linked) information sources that can be used in various research
                    scenarios.</p>
                <p> The Project DEPCHA, an Andrew W. Mellon funded cooperation of five US partners
                    and the <ref target="https://informationsmodellierung.uni-graz.at/en/">Centre
                        for Information Modelling at Graz University</ref>, aims to link the
                    knowledge domain of economic activities to historical accounting records. For
                    this purpose the so-called <ref target="/o:depcha.bookkeeping"
                        >Bookkeeping-Ontology</ref> is developed. DEPCHA creates a publication hub
                    for digital editions on the web, converting multiple formats into RDF and
                    publishing these alongside the transcriptions and allows the usage of various
                    retrieval and visualization functionalities, as well as interoperability and
                    reuse of information in the sense of Linked Open Data.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="discovery">
                <head type="sub">Discover the data that lies hidden in DEPCHA.</head>
                <p>This is the experimental part of DEPCHA, which is still under development. In
                    this section, customized resource discovery strategies will be implemented to
                    explore the entire DEPCHA dataset in different ways.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="ontology">
                <head type="sub">Structure transactions in accounting records.</head>
                <p>According to that historical data must be prepared and structured based on a
                    formal set of rules. The <ref target="/o:depcha.bookkeeping"
                        >Bookkeeping-Ontology</ref>, a conceptual data model based on <ref
                        target="https://www.cidoc-crm.org/">CIDOC-CRM</ref>, is developed in an
                    ontology engineering process, involving historians, software developers and
                    digital humanists. In a nutshell:</p>
                <p>The ontology formalizes the interpretation of a transaction as a combination of
                    transfers of economic goods and money from one accounting object to another. In
                    this way, semantic structures, representing transaction, can be defined from
                    different sources and source types. Thus, workflows can be set up to normalize
                    these semantics.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="tutorial">
                <head type="sub">Learn how to prepare your data for DEPCHA.</head>
                <p>To make this possible, it is necessary that the data is structured and normalized
                    in a consistent way. The detailed tutorials on this page illustrate a variety of
                    examples and annotation possibilities to ensure that data is structured
                    appropriately for DEPCHA. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
