<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en">DEPCHA - Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative for Historical
                    Accounts</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:lang="de">Karl-Franzens-Universität Graz</publisher>
                <publisher xml:lang="en">University of Graz</publisher>
                <date when="2018">2018</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date when="2018">2018</date>
                <name type="place">Graz, Austria</name>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
                <div type="header">
                    <head>How to Semantic Bookkeep</head>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>TEI/XML</head>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p>Coming in the future! :)</p>
                        <p>huhu</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>CSV</head>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p>hihi</p>
                        <p>Coming in the future! :)</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            <div>
                <head>How to Ingest Data into GAMS</head>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>hihi</p>
                    <p>To start a new ingest process, choose 'File' and 'Ingest objects'. The dialogue box allows you to configure mass ingest scenarios for 
                        cirilo:dfgMETS and cirilo:TEI objects. Choose one of the two content model types and click either 'From filesystem' 
                        (which opens the directory selection dialogue), 'From eXist' (which allows you to connect to an eXist database).
                        All files from the selected directory (including also all sub-directories) or database will be imported. 
                         Files are validated upon ingest, i.e. if the source document is not valid, the ingest process fails and 
                         an error message occurs. If you use the ingest function, it is highly recommended to specify your PIDs in the source documents using the element <hi style="code">&lt;idno @type="PID"&gt;</hi>.
                        Please note, that if two documents specify the same PID, the first
                        one ingested will be updated with the content of the second one for all content models except for the cirilo:Ontology model for RDF. 
                        If more than one RDF document specifies the same PID value in the @rdf:resource of the <hi style="code">&lt;void:Dataset&gt;</hi> the content of the second one will be added to the first one and will not replace it!</p>
                    <p>
                        The DC metadata specified in the ingest dialogue box will be copied for all ingested objects. A log file with details on the process is provided by the client; Either click
                        'Show log' or open it from the ingest source directory in your filesystem, where it is saved.
                        The ingest of objects can also be simulated. This option is used to detect possible errors in the log files, before actually starting huge mass ingest operations. 
                        If you want to run a simulation, tick the corresponding box.
                    </p>
                    <figure type="web" source="/cirilo_doku/img/ingestobjects.jpg" ana="Ingest objects dialogue box"/>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
