<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
    <dc:title>Merchant accounting and profits in Europe and the Americas, 1750-1800 (MARPROF)</dc:title>
    <dc:subject>Business Accounts</dc:subject>
    <dc:description>When it comes to the day-to-day practices of XVIIIth-century merchants, such as
        their accounting records, the entrepreneurial strategies they developed, and more generally
        everything connected to profit-making, quantified analysis is hard to come by, not to say
        nonexistent. A series of obstacles have stymied most attempts at such analysis, among which
        the indeterminacy of the price and quality scales used to describe goods, the fact that
        goods cannot usually be traced through the series of transactions they underwent, the lack
        of accounting precision, both with respect to overhead and to assets, etc. Therefore, the
        MARPROF proejct aims at recapturing the internal coherence of these practices, and at
        reaching a better understanding of merchant strategies both quantitatively and
        qualitatively. This digitization project should help to gain a complete vision of a series
        of merchant situations, not so much through balance sheets which in most cases cannot be
        drawn, but by associating each account to a series of sets of goods/prices, each of which is
        in turn linked to a trend toward profitability (or loss). It is hoped to achieve an
        equivalent to the "landscape" each merchant perceived through his accounts, which was
        actually a qualitative perception of his overall profit situation, rather than a quantified
        balance sheet of his actual profit. A second stage of the project will consist in
        cross-studying these accounting landscapes with the qualitative data one can derive from
        merchant correspondence from the same individuals and at the same time, a process of
        comparison which should enable us to link the accounting percception to specific profit
        strategies.</dc:description>
    <dc:publisher>Institute Centre for Information Modelling, University of Graz</dc:publisher>
    <dc:contributor>Pierre Gervais</dc:contributor>
    <dc:date>1750-1800</dc:date>
    <dc:coverage>Europe</dc:coverage>
    <dc:coverage>America</dc:coverage>
    <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
    <dc:relation>http://archives-web.univ-paris1.fr/marprof/</dc:relation>
    <dc:format>RDF</dc:format>
    <dc:type>Collection</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
